Guide to the Native American Educational Services Community Board Training Project Records 1978-1995
University of Chicago Library
Native American Educational Services. Community Board Training Project. Records
1978-1995
9.25 linear feet (17 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The Community Board Training Project was an educational program of Native American Educational Services College. CBTP addressed the occupational training needs of Native Americans in the Chicago area, as well as cooperative efforts among various Native American organizations in the area. This collection forms part of the archives of Native American Educational Services, and consists of 9.25 linear feet of materials related to CBTP's administration, programming, and work with other organizations. This collection also contains some materials regarding the relationship between the CBTP and several other organizations in the Chicago area.
Information on Use
Access
Series VII contains student records, restricted until 2061.
The remainder of the collection is open for research, with no restrictions.
Historical Note
The Native American Educational Services (NAES) College began the Community Board Training Project (CBTP) as a 2 ½ year program in 1979. The CBTP continued through 1983. During that time, the CBTP was structured to help organizations serving the Native American community to function more efficiently. With Louis Delgado as its director, CBTP sponsored workshops which focused on training in the concepts behind community service agencies, including effective management and technical skills such as planning fiscal management, improving public relations, filing, hiring and using computer technology. During the course of its existence, the program expanded and sought to provide resource materials to community organizations and to offer them technical assistance.
Scope Note
This collection represents the activities of the Community Board Training Project (CBTP) and of Native American Educational Services (NAES) College, CBTP's sponsoring organization. The collection forms part of the archives of Native American Educational Services. Materials in the collection focus on administration, programming, and work with other organizations. It is arranged in seven series, some of which are organized into topical sections. While the collection spans the years 1978-1995, most of the material dates from 1980-1984. The collection is closely related to the records of Chicago American Indians Community Organization Conference (CAICOC), which was itself an outgrowth of CBTP.
Series I: Administrative, contains the administrative records of CBTP, including quarterly reports, student records, correspondence, information generated by the Advisory Board, evaluation of the program and training needs assessment, and a record of the Chicago American Indian Community Service Directory. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
Series II: Courses, contains course materials generated by the courses, workshops and seminars produced by CBTP. These courses included the American Indian Bilingual/Bicultural Teacher Training Program, courses on economics and development, finance and management, education and human services and personal competence. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
Series III: Financial, contains materials relating to funding and grants obtained by the organization during the course of its programming. This series also includes some accounts payable and accounts receivable materials. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
Series IV: Program Development, includes materials which trace the historical development of the programs. It contains a great deal of information from 1980, the first full year of the program. Some of the materials included are proposals and other developmental documents. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
Series V: Organizations, provides a record of some of the federal, private, educational, and financial organizations which participated in the CBTP program, including organization information, requests for technical assistance and other information about the support provided by CBTP. This includes the Bureau of Indian Affairs and the American Indian Center. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
Series VI: Publications, Media, and Public Relations, contains various handbooks and manuals, and articles, as well as public relation information for organizations and individuals that offered resources and support for CBTP. It has been divided into several sections. The series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
Series VII: Restricted, contains student records from courses and seminars held by CBTP which are restricted for 80 years. This series has been arranged alphabetically.
Series VIII: Oversize, contains two examples of letterheads for the Chicago American Indian Community Organization Conference.
Related Resources
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Native American Educational Services. Chicago American Indians Community Organization Conference. Records
Subject Headings
NAES College; Indian universities and colleges -- United States; Indians of North America; Indians of North America -- Education (Higher)
INVENTORY
- Series I: Administrative
  Series I contains the administrative records of Community Board Training Project. This includes meeting minutes, quarterly reports, student records, correspondence, information generated by the Advisory Board, evaluation of the program and training needs assessment, and a record of the Chicago American Indian Community Service Directory. This series also includes the mailing records of the CBTP office. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - Advisory Board, meeting minutes, correspondence, schedules, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Board, meeting minutes, correspondence, schedules, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Advisory Board, newsletters, member lists and information, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chicago American Indian Community Service Directory, correspondence, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chicago American Indian Community Service Directory, directories of members and businesses, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chicago American Indian Community Service Directory, miscellaneous news releases, drafts, and information, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chicago American Indian Community service Directory, organization data, correspondence with other schools, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Community Board Training Project, staff meetings, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Community Board Training Project, staff meetings, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "A Final Evaluation," The Community Board Training Project, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Finding aids and progress reports, The Community Board Training Project, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Forms used by Native American Educational Services College and the Community Board Training Project, no date (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Government documents, 1975-1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Job descriptions and postings, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Library reference lists, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mailing lists and labels, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mailing lists and labels, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Mailing procedures and policies, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Meeting minutes, American Indian Center, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Meeting minutes, Community Board Training Project, May 28, 1980 – December 29, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Meeting minutes, Community Board Training Project, January 14, 1981 – December 21, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Meeting minutes, Community Board Training Project, December 1982 – May 10, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Meeting minutes, Community Board Training Project, sponsored community meetings, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Meeting minutes, Native American Educational Services, Chicago Site Board Meeting, 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Meeting minutes, Program Assistance Committee, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Memos within the Native American Educational Services College, 1981-1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Native American Educational Services College, Chicago Site Board, by-laws and minutes, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Native American Educational Services College, Chicago Site Board, by-laws and minutes, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Native American Educational Services College, Chicago Site Board, by-laws and minutes, 1982-1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Native American Educational Services, staff, meeting minutes, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Native American Educational Services, staff, meeting minutes, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Native American Educational Services, staff, meeting minutes, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Needs assessment, questionnaires, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Needs assessment, results, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Outgoing letters, September – December, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing letters, January – December, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing letters, January – December, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Personnel, evaluation forms, luncheons, 1981-1983 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Personnel policies, "Personnel Policies – Problems in Development and Policy Compliance," 1983 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Photos for data fact book, no date (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Program evaluation, correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Program evaluation, forms and questionnaires, evaluation reports, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Quarterly reports, Community Board Training Project, 1980-1984 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Student listings, Community Board Training Project, 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Student records and lists, Community Board Training Project, 1979-1982 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Student records, registration forms, 1979-1983 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Travel documents, 1981-1983 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Series II: Courses
  Series II contains course materials generated by the courses, workshops and seminars produced by the Community Board Training Project. These courses included the American Indian Bilingual/Bicultural Teacher Training Program, courses on economics and development, finance and management, education and human services and personal competence. There are also study resources and workbooks for several seminars. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - Adult Learning Center, information, assistance request forms, 1980-1984 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Class listings, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Class listings, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Class listings and new class information, no date (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Classes, "American Indian Bilingual/Bicultural Teacher Training Program," planning and budgets, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Classes, "American Indian Bilingual/Bicultural Teacher Training Program," proposal, description, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Classes, "American Indian Bilingual/Bicultural Teacher Training Program," teacher resumes, budgets, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Classes, "American Indian Bilingual/Bicultural Teacher Training Program," teacher resumes, grant applications, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Classes, "American Indian Bilingual/Bicultural Teacher Training Program," budget revisions, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Classes, "American Indian Bilingual/Bicultural Teacher Training Program," government documents, 1985-1986 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Classes, "Basic Accounting Techniques in Community Organizations," 1982 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Classes, "Contemporary Government Issues for Indian Organizations," 1982 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Classes, "Crisis Intervention in Human Services," 1983 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Classes, "Dynamics of Community Board Membership," 1979-1984 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Classes, "Dynamics of Government and Law," 1984 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Classes, "Fundamentals of Federal Indian Law," 1981 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Classes, "History of Indians in Chicago – Defining a Community," 1982 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Classes, "Management Issues in Indian Community Organizations," 1981 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Classes, "Management Issues in Indian Community Organizations II – Financial," 1981 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Classes, "Management Issues in Indian Community Organizations III – Corporate Responsibility,' 1981 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Classes, miscellaneous information and mailings, 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Classes, "Native American Literature," 1983 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Classes, "Personnel Supervision," 1982 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Classes, "Program Design of Community Service Agencies," 1982 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Classes, "Role of Community Boards in Indian Organizations" I – Function, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Classes, "Role of Community Boards in Indian Organizations," II – Procedures, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Classes, "Role of Community Boards in Indian Organizations," III – Legal Responsibilities, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Classes, "Role of Community Boards in Indian Organizations," I – Function, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Classes, "Role of Community Boards in Indian Organizations," ii – Procedures, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Evaluations, questionnaires and reports, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Other Institutions, Northwestern University, application and information, 1983-1984 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Other Institutions, University of Illinois at Chicago, seminars and services, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Seminars, "Assertiveness Training," outlines, coursework, questionnaires, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Seminars, "Assertiveness Training," correspondence, memos, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Seminars, "Assertiveness Training," descriptions, registration, and questionnaires, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Seminars, "Business Writing Class," articles, registration, outlines, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Seminars, "Chicago Political Systems," information and registration, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Seminars, "Developing Community Board Policy," announcement, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Seminars, "Effective Employee Interactions," brochures, announcements, registration, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Seminars, "Effective Group Working Skills," registration and agenda, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Seminars, "Effective Slide Sound Tape Presentation," course information, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Seminars, "Employee Benefits for Community Organizations," announcement and questionnaires, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Seminars, "Executive Search and Selection," announcements, registration, proceedings, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Seminars, "Filing Systems Training Session," agenda, announcements, proceedings, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Seminars, "Fundamentals of Training Techniques," registration, announcements, applications, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Seminars, "Graphics Design," announcements, reports, information, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Seminars, 'Guidance and Counseling in Indian Community Organizations," applications, registration, outlines, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Seminars, "Journalism Workshop," articles, information, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Seminars, "Media Workshop," announcements, conference reports, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Seminars, miscellaneous flyers and announcements for seminars and courses, 1980-1981 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Seminars, miscellaneous flyers and announcements for seminars and courses, 1982-1986 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Seminars, "Public Relations in Community Organizations," flyers and information, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Seminars, "Public Speaking," list of attendees, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Seminars, "Secretary Workshop," worksheets and notes, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Seminars, "Self-Management Project," list of attendees, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Seminars, "Veteran's Workshops," announcement, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Study resources, workbooks, 1981-1984 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Study resources, workshop information, 1985-1986 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Series III: Financial
  Series III contains materials relating to funding and grants obtained by the organization during the course of its program. This series also includes some accounts payable and accounts receivable materials, which includes information and correspondence with several donating foundations and individuals. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - Administration for Native Americans, applications and information, 1979-1985 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Donating foundations, United Presbyterian Church, correspondence, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Donating foundations, United States Department of Health and Human Services, applications and correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Donating foundations, United States Department of Health and Human Services, applications and correspondence, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Donating foundations, United States Department of Housing and Urban Development, applications and information, 1978-1981 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Donating foundations, United States Department of Labor, "Summary and Analysis of the Job Training Partnership Act of 1982," 1982 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Donating foundations, United Way, brochures, correspondence, information, applications, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Donating foundations, United Way, correspondence, information, applications, 1980-1982 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Donating foundations, Untied Way, correspondence, information, applications, 1982-1984 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Donating foundations, United Way, correspondence, information, applications, 1984-1985 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Donating foundations, Uptown Chicago Commission, invitation, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Donating foundations, Westside Access Center, correspondence and applications, 1984-1985 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Donating foundations, Wieboldt Foundation, correspondence and application, 1983-1985 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Donating foundations, Woods Charitable Fund, Incorporated, correspondence, applications, 1982-1985 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Donating individuals, Donnelley, Gaylord, correspondence, information, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Donating individuals, miscellaneous donors, letters and forms, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Federal Register, grant applications, 1981-1982 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Form for funding, memo, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Library, book sales records, donations, budgets, 1982-1985 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, brochures, booklets, correspondence, records, 1978-1983 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Student aid, conference information, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - "Title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964," photocopy, circa 1980 (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Program Development
  Series IV includes materials which trace the historical development of the Community Board Training Project and its programs. It contains a great deal of information from 1980, the first full year of the program, and the early eighties while the program was active. Some of the materials included are proposals and other developmental documents. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - "Declaration of Indian Purpose," The Voice of the American Indian, circa 1980 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Articles, by-laws, case studies and reports, 1978-1980 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Articles, by-laws, case studies and reports, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Articles, case studies, reports, booklet, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Articles, correspondence, reports, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Reports, correspondence, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Reports, summaries, notes, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, correspondence, report, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Credibility file, correspondence, 1980-1982 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Education, articles, reports, 1981-1987 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Undated materials, articles, reports, handwritten notes, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Series V: Organizations
  Series V provides a record of some of the organizations which participated in the Community Board Training Project program, including organization information, requests for technical assistance and other information about the support provided by CBTP. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - American Indian Brotherhood, correspondence, directories, 1980-1981 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - American Indian Business Association, correspondence, announcements, reports, handwritten notes, 1979-1985 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - American Indian Center, correspondence, announcements, programs, reports, 1979-1985 (Box 12, Folder 7-8)
  - American Indian Economic Development Association, articles of incorporation, correspondence, by-laws, minutes, 1984-1985 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - American Indian Health Service, newsletter, correspondence, information, 1980-1983 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Bo-Sho-Nee-Gee Drop-In Center, service receipt, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Boards and staff, lists of Native American community agencies, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - IEIOHE, report, requests for assistance, 1980-1981 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Indian Council Fire, correspondence, notes, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Little Big Horn High School, request for technical assistance and report forms, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Mexican Community Committee, handwritten notes, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Native American Committee, correspondence, technical assistance requests and reports, 1982-1983 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Native American Educational Services, annual reports, forms, brochure, correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Native American Outpost, correspondence, by-laws, report forms, brochure, 1982-1983 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Native American Program, agenda and announcement, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - O-Wai-Ya-Wa, minutes, notes, lists of graduates, reports, 1980-1983 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Organization list, no date (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Rockford, Illinois Title IV Program, correspondence, handwritten notes, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Saint Augustine's Indian Center, brochures, correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 13, Folder 15)
- Series VI: Publications, Media, and Public Relations
  Series VI contains various handbooks and manual, articles, and public relations information on funding organizations and individuals that supported the Community Board Training Project and used its resources. It has been divided into several sections, including office documents, evaluations, relations with funding organizations, handbooks and manuals, and publications from the Community Board Training Project. The series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - Books ordered, list and ledger, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Brochures, letterheads, 1980-1981 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Documents, correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Documents, program descriptions and overviews, 1982-1986 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Documents, project files, no date (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Documents, reports and proposals, statements of purpose, 1983-1990 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Evaluations and surveys, American Indian Center Survey, list of members, no date (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Evaluations and surveys, "The Community Board Training Project, Native American Educational Services College, A Final Evaluation," 1983 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Evaluations and surveys, "An Evaluation Report of the 1981-1982 Program Year of the Community Board Training Project of the Native American Educational Services College," 1982 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Evaluations and surveys, health survey statistics, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 3)